Ross Moffett Papers
Ross Moffett Papers
1916-1964
Moffett, Ross.
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence (1921-1962); clippings, exhibition catalogs and invitations (1916-1945); and photographs. Also, letters and printed material related to Moffett’s Federal Art Project post office murals in Holyoke and Sommerville, Massachusetts, and his Presidential mural at the Eisenhower Foundation in Abilene, Kansas. Letters of Gerrit A. Beneker, Louis Bouché, Charles Burchfield, Julia Morrow DeForest, John Davis Hatch, Marston Hodgin, Alexander J. Kostellow, Tod Lindenmuth, and Louise Orwig. Also, letters and printed material related to the Provincetown Art Association, for which Moffett served as an officer.
149773
Biographical History
American painter.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1916 to 1964, the Ross Moffett Papers comprises correspondence and memorabilia of the American painter. Focusing on Moffett's mural work for the Federal Art Project and the Eisenhower Foundation, the collection reflects the professional career of the Provinetown, MA artist.
Letters and a variety of printed material related to art projects and museum shows constitute Correspondence-Subject Files. Correspondence includes that with artists (Gerrit A. Beneker, Louis Bouché, Charles Burchfield, Julia Morrow DeForest, Marston Hodgin, Tod Lindenmuth, R.E. McCullough, Louis Orwig); curators (John Davis Hatch, Alexander J. Kostellow); museums (Carnegie Institute, Corcoran Gallery of Art, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts); and professional organizations (National Academy of Design, Provincetown Art Association). Materials from the United States Treasury Department and the Eisenhower Foundation relate respectively to Moffett's post office murals in Holyoke and Sommerville, MA, and his presidential mural in Abilene, KS. Correspondence pertaining to the Committee for the Preservation of the Province Lands details Moffett's efforts to protect the boundaries of the National Sea Shore against commercialization.
Memorabilia consists of photographs, printed material, receipts, and writings by others. Photographs document a class at the Art Institute of Chicago, an exhibition in Provincetown, and two paintings by an unidentified artist. Clippings (1917-1961) and exhibition catalogs and invitations (1916-1945) constitute Printed material. Writings by others include a short history of Provincetown printmakers by Ada Gilmore Chaffee and exhibition notes by Tod Lindenmuth.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by title or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Beneker, Gerrit A. (Gerrit Albertus), 1882-1934.; Bouché, Louis, 1896-1969.; Burchfield, Charles, 1893-1967.; DeForest, Julie Morrow.; Hatch, John Davis.; Hodgin, Marston.; Kostellow, Alexander J.; Lindenmuth, Tod.; Moffett, Ross.; Orwig, Louise; Eisenhower Foundation (Abilene, Kan.); Federal Art Project.; Provincetown Art Association.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art and state.; Mural decoration and painting, American; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ross Moffett
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - A-Z (Box 1)
  - Beneker, Gerrit A., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Bouché, Louis, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Burchfield, Charles, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1930-1933 (Box 1)
  - Committee for the Preservation of Province Lands, 1959-1962 (Box 1)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1939-1943 (Box 1)
  - DeForest, Julia Morrow, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Milton, See Eisenhower Foundation (Abilene, KS) murals
  - Eisenhower Foundation (Abilene, KS) murals, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Federal Art Project, See United States. Treasury Department. Public Works of Art Project
  - Frachtenberg, Harry, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - Hatch, John David, 1934-1935; 1938 (Box 1)
  - Hodgin, Marston, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Kostellow, Alexander J., 1930 (Box 1)
  - Lindenmuth, Tod, 1959 (Box 1)
    See also Memorabilia: Writings by others
  - McCullough, R.E., 1930 (Box 1)
  - National Academy of Design, 1921-1944 (Box 1)
    See also Eisenhower Foundation (Abilene, KS) murals
  - New York World's Fair, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Orwig, Louise, 1944; outgoing 1952 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1934-1939 (Box 1)
  - Provincetown Art Association, 1938-1940; undated (Box 1)
    Art in Narrow Streets (1964) / Ross Moffett
  - United States. Treasury Department. Public Works of Art Project, 1933-1940 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs, 4 (Box 1)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1917-1961; undated (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1919; 1931,; undated (Box 1)
    - Exhibition invitations, 1916-1945 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      Hawthorne Memorial Gallery proposal
      Provincetown April issue (c1934)
      Reality Vol. 1 No. 1, Spring 1953
  - Receipts, 6 (Box 1)
  - Writings by others
    - Chaffee, Ada Gilmore, "Provincetown Printmakers (Box 1)
    - Lindenmuth, Tod, exhibition notes (Box 1)